{"tossups": [{"question": "One of these people, who authored a manual of their grammar called the<em> Razos</em>, was Raimon Vidal. Another of these people is the subject of Robert Browning\u2019s poem<em> Sordello</em>. William IX, Duke of Aquitaine is often called the first of these people, whose primary output consisted of cansos and sirventes and who often used the Occitan language to tell stories about chivalrous themes. For ten points, name these medieval European poets who wrote songs of courtly love.", "answer": "<b> troubadour</b>s (prompt on musician and/or poet until \u201cpoet\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This program was criticized for a slow reaction to the Church Rock mill disaster in 1979. This program began after schools on 93rd and 99th Street were harmed by Hooker Company\u2019s poor management of a landfill in Niagara Falls, New York, leading numerous schoolchildren to be poisoned. Love Canal, the Valley of the Drums, and other locations are judged in the Hazard Ranking System by, for ten points, what federal program that empowers the EPA to clean up hazardous waste sites?", "answer": "<b> Superfund</b> (prompt on the EPA or Environmental Protection Agency before mentioned; prompt on CERCLA or the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city fell under the rule of the patron Ottone\u2019s [oh-toh-nay\u2019s] family after he won the Battle of Desio against Napo della Torre. Twelve \u201ccaptains and defenders of liberty\u201d were elected to write this city\u2019s laws when it was briefly reorganized into the Golden Ambrosian Republic following the fall of the Visconti family. After that republic fell, this city was ruled by the Sforzas. For ten points, name this capital of Lombardy, a city in Northern Italy.", "answer": "<b> Milan</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "An opera about people working in this profession opens with a corrected quote from the Smyth Report and features the central character singing the aria \u201cBatter my Heart, three person\u2019d God.\u201d Another opera titled for one of these people includes scenes entitled \u201cTrain,\u201d \u201cBed,\u201d and \u201cSpaceship,\u201d as well as interludes known as \u201cknee plays\u201d over the course of its five-hour run time. A John Adams opera set at Los Alamos depicts, for ten points, what profession depicted in<em> Doctor Atomic</em> and Philip Glass\u2019s<em> Einstein</em> <em>on the Beach</em>?", "answer": "<b> scientist</b>s (accept specific types of scientists, such as nuclear<b> physicist</b>s)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "A ruler of this country had, in his earlier military career, led a fleet against Alfredo Acton that tried to break the Otranto Barrage. This country, which faced the 1918 Aster Revolution, was the site of a very short-lived Soviet Republic led by Bela Kun. During World War II, Miklos Horthy was a regent of, for ten points, what European country that was ruled by the medieval Arpad dynasty and, until World War I, part of a dual monarchy with Austria?", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Hungary</b> (prompt on Austria-Hungary before \u201cMiklos\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man stored the remains of his long-time ally, Rwandan President Juvenal Habyarimana, at his palace in Gbadolite, this politician\u2019s so-called \u201cVersailles of the Jungle.\u201d This leader deposed Patrice Lumumba and was deposed himself by Laurent Kabila in 1997. This leader changed his own name to establish pro-Africa cultural awareness and changed the name of his country to Zaire. For ten points, name this leopard print hat-wearing dictator who ruled in the Democratic Republic of the Congo.", "answer": "Joseph D\u00b4esir\u00b4e<b> Mobutu</b> (or<b> Mobutu</b> Sese Seko Kuku Ngbendu Wa Za Banga)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In May 2015, this country became the first to pass a referendum legalizing same-sex marriage, and it is considering another referendum to repeal the abortion-forbidding Article 9 of its constitution. Leo Varadkar\u2019s elevation as leader of this country made him the first biracial leader of a European country, and the first LGBT person to hold the title of Taoiseach [tee-shuck]. For ten points, name this country where Varadkar leads Fine Gael [finn-neh GALE], the rival party to Fianna F\u00b4ail [fee-uh-nuh FOIL] and Sinn F\u00b4ein [shin FAYN] in Dublin.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Ireland</b> (do not accept Northern Ireland)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The longest serving Attorney General in US history began his term under this president. William Wirt served this man, who warmed relations with Britain by starting to demilitarize the Great Lakes via the Rush-Bagot treaty. William Plumber prevented this man from becoming the second unanimously elected President. During this man\u2019s administration, Florida was purchased by his Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams. For ten points, name this US President who limited European involvement in the Americas with his namesake doctrine.", "answer": "James<b> Monroe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The First Amendment was applied to this industry in the so-called<em> Miracle</em> case involving distributor Joseph Burstyn. Joseph Breen held a powerful regulatory position in this industry when it was governed by the Hays Code. Dalton Trumbo was among a group of ten people who were blacklisted from this industry by the House Un-American Activities Committee in 1947. For ten points, name this industry once heavily censored by the MPAA, which today rates its products with tags such as PG-13.", "answer": "<b> film</b> industry (accept equivalents like<b> motion picture</b> industry; accept<b> Hollywood</b>; accept <b>Hollywood</b> Ten; do not accept or prompt on television)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s army inspector designed an artillery improvement in the \u201cSystem of 1805\u201d and notoriously ordered all cats to be hanged. This tsar met with Napoleon on a raft in the Neman River, where they agreed to the Treaty of Tilsit. After this man\u2019s death, supporters of his brother started the Decembrist Revolt. Russia was brought into the Congress of Vienna by, for ten points, what tsar who was succeeded by Nicholas I after his 1825 death?", "answer": "<b> Alexander I</b> (or<b> Alexander Pavlovich</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man is the second-longest serving Senator in US history.", "answer": "Daniel<b> Inouye</b> ([in-oh-ay], but be lenient)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s actions created 20,000 martyrs in his capital city of Nicomedia. This man became emperor after defeating Carinus at the Battle of the Margus. This man, who declared a price ceiling in the Edict of Maximum Prices, created a new ruling system after the Crisis of the Third Century before eventually retiring to his palace in Split to grow cabbage. The Tetrarchy was instituted by, for ten points, what Roman emperor who began the final Roman persecution of the Christians and abdicated the throne in 305 AD?", "answer": "<b> Diocletian</b> (accept Gaius Aurelius Valerius<b> Diocletian</b>us Augustus, but do not accept or prompt on any of the other names alone; accept<b> Diocles</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The British branch of this movement was kickstarted by a Bryan Robertson exhibition at Whitechapel; among the works exhibited there were a collage of an advertisement for a vacuum next to a muscular man holding a (+) lollipop. Another artist from this movement showed a woman thinking that she\u2019d \u201crather sink than call Brad for help.\u201d One artist who worked in this movement used silk-screening to repeatedly depict subjects like (*) </b>Chairman Mao and Marilyn Monroe. For ten points, name this artistic movement that used subjects from mass-media culture and included artists like Roy Lichtenstein and Andy Warhol.", "answer": "<b> Pop</b> Art", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>In 1961, this state\u2019s Parchman Farm prison was the site of the detention of more than 300 Freedom Riders. This state\u2019s Sovereignty Commission spied on the civil rights movement</b> <b>here and funded the legal defense of murderer Byron (+)</b> <b>De La Beckwith. This state\u2019s</b> <b>Freedom Democratic Party attempted to gain official recognition at the 1964 (*)</b> Democratic National Convention, but was rejected in favor of the all-white delegation. For ten points, name this state where Medgar Evers was murdered in 1963 in its capital of Jackson.", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>To support this policy, the Duke of Richmond formed the CAPS pressure group, while Richard Cobden and John Bright co-founded a league to protest this policy in Manchester.</b> <b>Charles Pelham (+)</b> <b>Villiers was the \u201csolitary Robinson Crusoe\u201d calling for repeal of this</b> <b>policy in the House of Commons. The newspaper</b><em><b> The Economist</b></em><b> was founded to end these laws, which Prime Minister (*)</b> Robert Peel finally repealed during the Irish Potato Famine. For ten points, name this controversial set of 19th century tariffs and high duties on the import of grains into Great Britain.", "answer": "<b> Corn</b> Law(s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man used Omar Khayyam\u2019s quote \u201cSo I be written in the Book of Love\u201d to end a seven-hour speech, usually named either \u201cI Believe in the Law of Love\u201d or \u201cA Plea For</b> <b>Mercy,\u201d that was given during the (+)</b> <b>trials of Ossian Sweet\u2019s family. This man, who</b> <b>trials of Ossian Sweet\u2019s family. This man, who</b> <b>represented the killers Leopold and Loeb, questioned (*)</b> <b>represented the killers Leopold and Loeb, questioned (*)</b> William Jennings Bryan about the factual nature of the Bible during a 1925 show trial in Tennessee. For ten points, name this attorney for the defense in the Scopes Monkey Trial.", "answer": "Clarence<b> Darrow</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Prior to this battle, the winning commander praised his officer Gisgo\u2019s skill despite his numerical disadvantage, and regularly sent cavalry to harass enemy combatants gathering water at the Aufidus River. The winning side at this battle wisely abandoned the (+) Fabian Strategy and deployed its center in a crescent formation, allowing their forces to doubly-envelop the armies led by (*)</b> Paullus and Varro. For ten points, name this 216 BC battle, a decisive victory for Hannibal during the Second Punic War, that followed his victories at Lake Trasimene and Trebia.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Cannae</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This country lost its independence after the Urabi revolt. This country initially rejected the Convention of London, but was forced to accept it after a siege of Acre.</b> <b>This country was nearly bankrupted due to the modernization under (+)</b> <b>Khedive</b> <b>Ismail, who attempted to improve its vital (*)</b> cotton industry. For ten points, name this north African country that was a British protectorate until Muhammad Naguib and the Free Officers Movement forced King Farouk to abdicate and flee Cairo.", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b> (accept Khedivate of<b> Egypt</b>; accept Arab Republic of<b> Egypt</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}